[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer org
slash software Jim Benson welcome to the
interview thank you very much for
joining your an idea very right yes that
is right cool
okay the Jim maybe not everyone knows
you and know what you who you are
could you maybe give a brief
introduction to yourself and what are
you doing and what have you already done
in your life okay so I'm Jim Benson I
write now I am the CEO of a company
called modus operandi and in the IT
world were best known for being both
Kanban pioneers and the creators of
personal Kanban so before owning this
company I had a software development
company that used agile practices and
sold those practices and our services to
government and while I owned that
company it became clear that there were
some things that agile did very well and
some other things that it didn't do so
well and that led to us in conjunction
with David Anderson to to start to
develop Kanban as a as an ideal and a
methodology mm-hmm and we get connected
with Kanban in the early days with with
David Henderson that's right like you
sleep in the same city right yes yes we
the the idea the the first conversations
about Kanban ever happened between David
and myself over
glasses of scotch at a pub right near my
house I was good yes and together with
em how I pronounced it right
tone-tone en yes Tony and Maria berry
yep she little water okay and you
developed it together like you person
can bond like you wrote the book also
together yeah so yeah so what what is
the core of personal can bond like the
bangles what is different from yet from
kanban okay so add its at its poor
personal Kanban has to two major rules
to visualize your work and to limit your
work in progress and the idea there is
that as knowledge workers and as
software developers we frequently take
on more work than we can handle and we
also often don't understand because
there's so many different contingencies
so many different tasks that could be
done at any given point in time what the
costs are of the choices that we're
making so the idea with the personal
Kanban was to show ourselves as
individuals and our teams what we're
working on why we're working on it
where there are opportunities for
collaboration and most importantly where
certain people are overworked mmm and
the two rules adjusted you visualize
what you what you're doing and you limit
what you're actually working on at the
moment
so that is correct sounds it that's
personal Kanban yes
the in a nutshell okay then thank you
very much for the interview Jim that's
it okay - easy now like when I when I so
I I just recently moved from from
in Germany to to Melbourne to work here
as a soccer coach and my wife and I have
we have a we have a little task board
like a little Kanban board but and I see
all the sticky note on the moment here
and and I think well let's put them all
into a draw in a box and put hide it
somewhere in the drawer under this
cupboard under the stairs somewhere so
from time to time I think if it's not a
why I visualize in it why why do you
think it's so important
well first off because we as as people
and and as as knowledge workers we have
a tendency to commit to do more things
over a period of time than we can
actually get done and part of the reason
for that is the knowledge work is
largely invisible and promises are
invisible so we promise to do a lot of
things either to ourselves or to other
people and when we go to act on those
promises we are surprised by the amount
of work we have all of a sudden it hits
us that we are overloaded and that we
have too much to do
so the goal was the personal Kanban and
the goal was visualizing that backlog is
to understand for yourself this is these
are the number of commitments that I've
made or these are the number of promises
that I've made and now when I act on
them I'm going to have to make choices
about which of those to do first and
every time I make a choice I will be
prioritizing one promise over another
and that can be a very uncomfortable
position to put yourself in so after
people tend to use personal Kanban for a
while they start to say okay you know
what I'm starting to promise too many
things I'm putting too many things into
my backlog I'd go do some stuff I have
to get some things done before
I go back and and then promise more
things mm-hmm and and that makes it
different from from it only and I can
normal to-do list where you were just
like well write down what you all have
to do but not think about the overload
or what is the different range to-do
list yeah so the to-do list is linear so
you can see no relationships in it and
it is it's static and so with with the
board itself when you're moving the
tickets you're seeing the flow of work
so not only do you see the things that
you have to do which may or may not be
in a to-do list but you also see what
happens when those when those tasks move
from one state to the next
now how long does it take you to
complete them which which of these were
fun to do
which of these were were difficult more
difficult than you anticipated which of
these you hate you know I never ever
want to do it again and so the more that
you start seeing those and then also
feeling those because when you're moving
the ticket from place to place it's a
very tactile system so you feel it with
your hands you feel the movement so you
get kinesthetic feedback by moving the
tickets and all of that creates a
learning system so you're learning more
about your work whereas with a to-do
list you just cross it off you basically
kill your work as you complete it I am
done and you cross it all out sounds
good yes and what well what is it what
makes it different between like what is
the difference from from Kanban known by
David Anderson and
and doesn't condone what to see what
makes it different well there's two or
there's several several major
differences but we'll focus on a couple
the first is that personal Kanban is
very much focused on the individual so
how do you as an individual feel about
the work that you're doing can other
people see the work that you're doing as
an individual and do you as an
individual have a good idea of what's on
your plate and what you can personally
deliver whereas capital K Kanban is
focused on the slow of work as as
business value through the businesses
value stream so there's there's that
difference the other difference is that
the granularity so personal Kanban tends
to be at the task level sometimes even
the sub task level whereas capital K
Kanban is going to be at the user story
level or the feature level and then the
last is that personal Kanban is about
psychological metrics how did that make
you feel you know when how much of this
can you complete and not overload
yourself those types of things whereas
capital K Kanban is focused on business
metrics which are you know what was your
cycle time how many how many features
did you get done since last week and
that type of thing that's what woody
might but what I was going to say was
that what's nice about David's capital K
Kanban system and personal Kanban is
that they dovetail quite nicely so it'd
be yeah so what I would I like to do
when I'm working with teams are working
with companies this was a team we'll set
up you know a capital K Kanban
but then the individuals on the team or
subgroups will have personal combine so
that they can maintain their own
personal whip limits while the team is
also maintaining its team whip limit
mm-hmm mm-hmm
yeah that was actually what I might like
what I guess like you can maybe scale it
in this way that you have one full team
and then for the individual or smaller
groups and personal one sounds good
exactly exactly well I found something
something on your website what what I
found a bit like weird or but I would
like to know what is what is what is in
there what is what is it about like I
found the topic for the future you are
interested or users and start working on
personal Kanban for kids and I I am the
father of a six year old daughter and I
thought what is this about
I cried straight sentence came into my
mind that stop planning start playing
and what is what is Kanban or closely
common for kids adult can you say
something about it so so yes kids bond
has I gone in many different directions
so it's been nice about personal Kanban
is that we released the meme and said
you know here is this loose structure
what what do you as the planet Earth
won't want to do with this and several
people look that immediately it started
to apply it to different elements of of
kids so some people like maritza Van
Hollen
in South Africa her kids have a the each
have personal common bonds for like
their work but then as a household they
have a chore Kanban
and as as a so as a household like on
Saturday mornings they will wake up and
they will attack the Detroit on bond
whereas what used to happen was mom
maritza
I would have to chase all of the kids
around and tell them what to do and when
to do it and then they would all hate
her now they all know that the sooner
that the tickets moved to done they have
the whole rest of the weekend to play
mm-hmm so there's they they're totally
motivated to wake up on Saturday morning
and run up to the car bond and just
start doing all of their chores because
they know that once all the tickets are
done they have total freedom in in other
cases therapists have used personal
convey on to help kids with either ADHD
or Asperger's get the focus that they
need so that they can they can complete
tasks so it gives them that little
additional structure that they need
we've used it with kids with children
who have cancer and weren't taking their
medication so instead of the con bond
with them and that's helped them either
take their medication or help the doctor
understand when and why they don't take
their medication there have been school
teachers that have used it a woman named
patty use personal Kanban to actually
teach her preschool students the
alphabet and before uh I think my
numbers are right but before in all of
the years before she tried personal
Kanban to do this her kids had about a
forty to sixty percent proficiency in in
the alphabet when they left from that
first year preschool and afterwards they
had about 85 to 90 percent proficiency
and
huge jar can I imagine or how does it
look like you have in the back sock
before 26 characters of the alphabet and
then you put the a in to do and you did
working on it and then the a is done and
you pour what I'll what what I also like
about what Patti did is she uh she
didn't she didn't become fixated in the
form of the Kanban so she knew that the
kids had to visualize their work and
they had to live with their work in
progress so each kid got a card and then
when they were learning the letters they
were able to across their card write
different letters to signify that they
had I believe it was first be able to
identify the letter and the second one
was spell a word with the letter in it
and I think there was some third stage I
can't remember what it was but the kids
would write those across there and then
when they got the three letters then
they were done and they can move on to
the next card and um so and it was
really cool and the the interesting
thing is that since these cards were all
on the wall learning your letters
suddenly became a social activity so the
kids were learning much more socially
than they had been in the past and they
she was having things happen like a
child would get sick and would be
completely freaking out at home that
that that they couldn't move their card
so they would actually you know prove at
home that they had mastered the skill
and then they would make a card and send
their parents to the preschool without
them to move their card and so uh so the
I and I can I can hook you up with Patti
and maritza if you if you'd like to talk
to them and there's yeah there's there's
there's literally there's literally
dozens of people that we know of that
have been working closely with kids
using different personal Kanban
principle
techniques which means that there's got
to be hundreds more that would be we
don't even know we're out there mm-hmm
yeah which on this wondering and
actually I think there's also like in in
learning it comes a droid principles or
lean or Kanban comes up more and more
and for example on the last agile coach
camp this year in Germany we and they
had one one person had the idea of an
agile school and it started with people
the open space and in the end it were
like 50 people sitting around in a fish
whole discussion so they thought it's
quite an is quite exciting what comes up
there in the future yeah thanks for
absolutely yeah yeah cool yeah I read
something that you're also interested in
a neck even can't pronounce it cognitive
dire basis is it right our biases and
yeah IOC's yet so what yeah I'm sorry
what is it and what's fascinating about
it so with the reason that this is
important to me is the in management and
in our assessments of ourselves we hold
ourselves to a standard that is
idealized and in being idealized it's
really hard for humans to obtain and we
don't understand how hard it is or why
it why it's hard and so cognitive the
field of cognitive psychology has part
of it cognitive biases and there are if
you look up list of cognitive bias in
Wikipedia you will get a list of I think
right now it's about a hundred and sixty
cataloged cognitive biases so these are
things that are going on inside our head
that make us a little less predictable
and a little less in control of our
lives than we
we are and and some of the big ones for
me the biggest one for me is one called
the planning fallacy and the planning
fallacy is exemplified by something
called Hofstadter's law and Hofstadter's
law states that human beings will
underestimate every task even if they
are aware of Hostetler's law and this
cognitive bias has been tested by
researchers all around the world it's
found to be cross-cultural cross gender
across everything the human beings tend
to underestimate every task they come
into contact with and when we get into
things like software development or all
knowledge work we find that we are
constantly beating ourselves up because
we're not estimating wellness and and
the fact is that we just we just don't
estimate very well there's a million
reasons why and I could talk for hours
on it but but but the fact is that we
can't and one of the reasons why that's
important with personal Kanban and with
capital K Kanban is because both tools
will allow you to measure how long it
really takes you to complete something
mm-hmm and and you can start to you can
start to estimate based on real numbers
as opposed to how long you feel it
should take you to complete something
and that's that's a huge shift that's an
absolutely huge shift another one of my
favorite cognitive biases is something
called the fundamental attribution error
and fundamental attribution error is
basically the brains tendency to blame
the last person you saw with something
for the state of that
something so if you have a set of
features that are supposed to be
delivered and they've gone completely
through dev and then they're stuck in
testing and they don't get released on
time people will blame testing for it
even though you know you could have had
250 days of development in 6 days of
testing it's still gonna be testing
fault because they were the last ones
with it even though they didn't have
enough time to do their jobs and so
Kanban because it's a visual system
tends to show more systemic reasons why
there are backups or why things happen
or why you know and why certain choices
that we made had certain impacts and
they helped us mitigate those cognitive
biases so if I if I get you right
the Kanban board and the visualizing of
the Kanban board has us not getting into
the trap of the our completely normal
cognitive biases yes ok so it's like it
helps us to get more reality into our
self-organization everyday exactly
exactly yeah yeah yeah we want we want
to measure work as it's really happening
yep okay well that's very cool yeah last
year there you got rewarded for the
brigid key award from the lean system
Society and I think it was because you
invent and promoted the lean coffee
format what is out what is what is the
lean coffee from it so with lean coffee
I people take a normal personal Kanban
the basic personal Kanban of ready doing
and done they'll put that down on a
table on sticky notes and then everybody
at the table gets some
some sticky notes they write down
anything that they want to talk about
that populates a backlog of stuff that
the table could talk about then each
individual member votes for two things
that they would like to talk about in
that list and that prioritizes the
backlog and then you simply speak about
those things in that order and this
format we started for two reasons the
first was that we wanted to have a lean
society in Seattle but we didn't want to
have to administer it which he didn't
want to have to run it so we wanted to
build an organization that would run
itself and so that organization like
like our teams needed the minimal amount
of structure and necessary to get
something done but it needed to have
enough structure so that you know it
would it would have a definition so if
you have no structure at all then you
just don't have a group but if you have
too much structure then you have to have
people around to enforce that structure
so with this minimal structure we were
able to look find a location as a
certain coffee shop in Seattle and say
every Wednesday morning we are going to
meet here and talk about mean stuff and
we're going to use this format and then
now if 30 people show up next week but
only one of those people has ever been
there before that's all it's necessary
you just need that one person who knows
where the post-it notes are yeah the
process is so easy the other thing that
it does is it when we use this for
meetings in with clients or we use this
for meetings at all is before meetings
had a strict agenda
and those agendas were usually written
by a person and that person would then
own the meeting so they would be like
the meeting commissary and everyone had
to listen to what they said and then it
would be the timekeeper and so on and so
forth and what happened then was
everybody that would come to the meeting
would then be in a power struggle with
that meeting owner to get their point
across or to get their thing out but
with Lync with Al in coffee format its
democratized everybody shows up the
meetings have a theme so you might say
anything you want to talk about about
you know finding your markets in Africa
you know write them down on post-it
notes and we'll talk about them if
somebody comes to the meeting and they
have their own thing that they want to
talk about and they write it on a
post-it note and no one votes for it
then it's not a power struggle anymore
between them and the meeting owner it's
them and absolutely everybody else and
that tends to diffuse you know people
from acting out or interrupting the
meetings or things like that and
gasoline coffee
I've loved running lean coffees there
they are fantastic and now worldwide
there are over a hundred lean coffees
going on public ones so it's in the
first day when I just hear this I
thought okay but normally it's a good
idea to have an agenda in a meeting
otherwise everyone talks starts talking
about what he likes and it takes hours
and it has no outcome of the meeting
especially for germs it is a big issue
and but I think if you have to seem like
what this meeting is about then the
important stuff comes up and you talk
about this this later notes that you
have to talk about in this way I have
still a little bit like an agenda okay
mm-hmm I got it yeah
I bought it yeah on the other
interesting thing there is that what I
found is Tony an and I will go in to be
working with the client and we will say
you know what are the biggest problems
here and they will say well the problems
are this and this other thing and so say
that's a and B our problems are a and B
and you go around and interview
everybody in the company and everybody
in the company agrees that it's a and B
so there's there's no doubt that the
problems are a and B and then we'll go
into a meeting you'll say you know we
just want to talk about you know what's
going on and how things are working so
whatever you guys want to talk about put
put an on posters notes and put it in in
the first two that pop up will be a and
B and there's a bunch of other stuff c d
e f g h i j k and then you get down to
about n RM and somebody will throw in a
topic just kind of off the top of their
head and really thought about it they
throw it down and everybody in the room
looks at it and immediately they're like
oh my god and it's apparent to everybody
immediately that that ticket was the
root cause of a and B so what also can
happen in building that collaborative
agenda for the meeting is that there's
this unconscious ideation session that
goes on where everybody's thinking about
things that they could talk about and
this has happened so many times I I
can't even express how many times this
happened anymore
the that a random topic ends up solving
a huge problem for the organization
simply because people finally had the
freedom to discuss whatever it was that
they need to discuss okay sounds good
[Music]
well beside Kanban what else are you
interested in like I read something that
you're interested in good food and oh
yes what else are you interested what
well food is food is going to be right
up there and I had any blessed I've been
blessed to last several years after
writing the personal Kanban book to have
been traveling around the world almost
constantly and so I have been able to
eat amazing food everywhere and I'm
looking forward to a few more years of
that before before I either get too fat
to fit on the plane or my heart explodes
or or something but but that's that's
been fantastic and gives me lots of lots
of funny stories to tell because I can
tell stories about like people who are
saying Americans no one in the world
eats more than America I'm like that's
because you haven't been to Bavaria
because I can tell you right now the any
Bavarian can eat Americans under the
table the only difference is they have
mountains so after they eat they go run
up and down the mountains non-stop and
then so that's why they're not as big in
gigantic as Americans but it's actually
exercised to if Americans just got some
exercise did you find so so there's that
and I've been loving traveling and
meeting meaning everybody but I have to
admit that a lot of a lot of what I
spend my time thinking about you know
even even with with those other loves is
is is workflow and how people can enjoy
their work better and be less stressed
and I really love this stuff yeah so I
see a if you're if you got tired or
bored by body in your Korea at the
moment you have the next one like
writing about good food on the planet
okay yes yes I even have I even have the
way I want to do that worked out so I
don't know I'm kind of hoping some days
I kind of wish that I'd wake up one
morning and two million people would
have bought the personal Kanban book and
I could say okay that's it I'm just
gonna focus on food for a while and we
get it we got to use what you say like
you travel around the world any plans to
go to Germany in the future um like
something I can't imagine that lean
Kanban Central Europe I don't know where
it's going to be this year but I'm
reasonably sure it's going to be in
Germany again so yeah I've been in
Germany every year at least twice since
2000 and 2005 so um and what's
frustrating is I haven't been super I
haven't been to Berlin since since the
wall came down
[Laughter]
so I was right over there right after
the wall came down and I haven't been
back since
so I would love to get back and go to
Berlin but um I've been everywhere else
okay
yep that's cool
maybe you see us I just had a look on
the internet where we next Lincoln
Montenegro is but I can't figure it out
at the moment okay well see it later
maybe in the footnote it was in Austria
this year yeah it was an Austrian right
yeah and I think it's in Germany again
and I theater and organizing it but I'm
not true actually
yet now you you jump book us out like
Mike a match my colleague of mine
translated to book during the last
couple of months the German book is out
what other languages are would be
translate or is it already translated in
different other language no German
German is the first okay
so and in it's out and I'm I'm still
waiting for my copies and I'm looking
forward to seeing them and then I will
read them very slowly as my as my German
is very very slow but what right now
it's being translated into French and we
are discussing with with a couple of
people translating it into Spanish cool
yeah then you have which is very Chinese
Mandarin and then you have the three
languages or even Germany as well okay
I'm good you want to say something for
the for the German reader who now is
interested in your book maybe it's
Pinterest in your book and well directly
to them mmm I'm so conversational that's
a interesting request so I think one of
the things that I'm I'm excited about
and haven't haven't yet found is I'm not
sure how to put this or even if it's a
good idea to say this on tape I'm I was
having a conversation with somebody on
one of my trips and they said you know
why do you think that the personal
conven work has been so popular in
Germany and because Germany is our
second second-biggest market
yeah I'm sure and and I believe that
there's that there's there's because
people are like you know is it is it
because you know Germans are very
systematic and they want to know exactly
what to do and exactly when to do it and
I said well
kindness I think that that's true but I
also think that that that there's part
of personal Kanban that resonates with
with Germans because Germans are very
systematic but they also understand that
the systems that they're building or
slightly flawed and so and that there's
that cognitive dissonance it like
bothers people you know it's like I'm
doing this and it's working but it's not
perfect and I know it can be more
perfect and that's what personal Kanban
is all about it's about saying you know
okay you've got this process right now
and it's working okay so keep working
with it because it's okay but always be
looking for ways that it can be better
and that improvement aspect I think is
is extremely attractive to to the way
the the way that Germans approach
problems yeah does that sound right it
is that's crazy it's not crazy actually
but for me it is how it bothered me from
time to time that I think it is working
but it's I think it's not the best thing
what we can have like and there you you
start thinking about and carrying the
sauce with oil for days with you around
here can be mm-hmm
yeah and that's I mean that's what
that's why I think that it's I think
because it comes right out at the
beginning and it says this is not
perfect but neither is anything else and
the major difference is that other other
systems try and convince you that
they're perfect and we're not going to
lie to you and say that yeah I have to
find it the way on your own cool well
let's have a look on the time I think it
was over 40 minutes
Jim Benton I think you want to say some
some something a lot some last roots for
the interview um well I mean the last
thing I'd like to say obviously that I'm
I'm very grateful for Formica
for her wonderful translation and that
I'm looking forward to to personal
Kanban being used in Germany even more
both with the English book and the
voyage book then thank you very much Jim
and maybe seus somewhere on the
conference and have a good time in
Seattle thanks for listening to se Radio
an educational program brought to you by
I Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se -
radio net to support us you can
advertise su Radio by clicking the de
crédit delicious or slash buttons on the
site or by talking about us on Facebook
Twitter or your own blog if you have
feedback specific to an episode please
use the commenting feature on the site
so that other listeners can respond to
your comments as well this and all of
the episodes of se radio is licensed
under the creative commons
two-point-five license please see the
website for details thanks again for
your support
[Music]
me